When working with documents, it
is important that the content
is structured effectively.
Windows has a number of tools
that allow you to do this.
And what we're going to be looking
at in this video is the tools that
you can find on the layout tab.
So if we clicked on the layout tab,
as you can see, there are three
sections here, and we're primarily
going to focus on the first two, which
is margins, page orientations, size,
columns, breaks and the way you can
indent and space the paragraphs around.
One of the tools that we're going to
look at first is the widows and orphans.
As you can see, it's unticked here.
By default, this will be
ticked in your Windows program.
If the widows and orphans box isn't
ticked, as you can see, when I start
pressing the enter key and moving
text further down the table and I
move onto a new page it actually
allows the splitting up of paragraphs.
So you can have information
starting on one line and not
finishing till the next line.
So if I just undo what I've done
there, and then I select the widows
and orphan control, make sure
that's ticked and select okay.
And then, press the enter key again, to
take the information onto the next page,
you will see that it jumps the paragraph.
It won't let you have just
one line on the previous page.
Just undo that.
Another feature that you may find
useful is the ability to keep paragraphs
together or lines in a paragraph together.
If you click on the paragraph
expansion control there, as you
can see, I've got keep lines
together ticked in that box there.
What this means is that when I press the
enter key and move text further down the
table, when it moves on to a new page,
it automatically moves a whole paragraph.
So it won't let you split a paragraph up.
I'll just move that back.
The next tool I'm going to
look at is the page break tool.
As you can see, all the information is
on one page there, but there is a blank
second page, but just back space that
and that everything is on one page.
So for example, I wish to
move the information from this
point forward onto a new page.
I can go to breaks and
select a page break.
Now that automatically moves
the information on to page two.
Now, that's fine.
But say, for example, I wanted to
have this page in landscape format
and keep this page in portrait format.
If I tried that now, so the cursor is
blinking, I've changed the orientation to
landscape, both pages change to landscape.
So I will just undo that.
What I need to do here is I need to undo
the page break that was inserted and
rather than insert a page break, I need
to insert a section break next page.
What this does it again, moves
the information on the page two
but, this allows me to format
this page in any way I want.
So I can now select the
orientation and landscape, and
it will only change that page.
As you can see if I go to the
home tab and use the show and hide
button to see the formatting that
is being applied, as you can see
there is a section break next page.
So that has basically moved
everything down and the
formatting that's applied to that.
The layout of that page can
be different to page one.
If I remove the show and hide, click
off that and then insert another section
break next page from the layout tab.
This third page can then be changed again.
So for example, I could go
back to portrait for that one.
So as you can see, I can have
one page in portrait, one page in
landscape, and then when I wish to
continue with the document, I can
have the third page back in portrait.
Another tool that you may find useful
is that you may present information in
column format, so rather than having
the text spread all across the page,
you may have a document where you
need to insert it in column format.
So if I place the cursor at the
front of the text on the first page.
And if I look at the columns
button, I click on that, I can
change it to 1, 2, 3 columns.
So just as an example, I'll
change that to two columns.
As you can see all of the text
has now been bunched up on the
left-hand side of the page.
If I just insert the cursor there
and press the enter key, as you can
see, it is now moving the text to
another column on the same page.
This can be useful if you're presenting
something such as a newsletter.
As your document increases in size
it would be useful to insert page
numbers so you can identify the pages
as the document grows to do this,
we need to go to the insert tab.
So I click on insert and as you
can see if I look along to the
header and footer section, there's
the option to insert page numbers.
So I can click on the page number and
it will ask me if I wish to place it
at the top of the page, to the bottom
of the page and the margin of the page.
For this one, I'm just going to
select the bottom of the page.
As you can see the variety of
formatting that can be applied to
the way the page number is entered.
For this one, I'm going to simply
select plain number two, and that
will insert a page number in the
footer section of the document.
So just click away from that.
And as you can see, that has
automatically inserted page numbers on
the three pages within this document.